<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ASA-BIOP Covariate Adjustment SWG</title>
<link>https://carswg.github.io/journal_club.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://carswg.github.io/journal_club.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Webpage for ASA-BIOP Covariate Adjustment SWG</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Adjustments with Many Regressors under Covariate-Adaptive Randomizations</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub7.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> Adjustments with Many Regressors under Covariate-Adaptive Randomizations</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: November 8th Friday, 11am-12pm ET.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Yichong Zhang from Singapore Management University</p>
<p><strong>Zoom link:</strong>: https://umich.zoom.us/j/7573650566</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Our paper discovers a new trade-off of using regression adjustments (RAs) in causal inference under covariate-adaptive randomizations (CARs). On one hand, RAs can improve the efficiency of causal estimators by incorporating information from covariates that are not used in the randomization. On the other hand, RAs can degrade estimation efficiency due to their estimation errors, which are not asymptotically negligible when the number of regressors is of the same order as the sample size. Ignoring the estimation errors of RAs may result in serious over- rejection of causal inference under the null hypothesis. To address the issue, we construct a new ATE estimator by optimally linearly combining the estimators with and without RAs. We then develop a unified inference theory for this estimator under CARs. It has two features: (1) the Wald test based on it achieves the exact asymptotic size under the null hypothesis, regardless of whether the number of covariates is fixed or diverges no faster than the sample size; and (2) it guarantees weak efficiency improvement over estimators both with and without RAs.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub7.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Covariate-Adjusted Randomization Analyzed with Randomization-Based Inference</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub6.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> Covariate-Adjusted Randomization Analyzed with Randomization-Based Inference</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: Oct 11th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Jonathan Chipman from University of Utah</p>
<p><strong>Zoom link:</strong>: https://umich.zoom.us/j/7573650566</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> Adjusting for covariates in the design and/or analysis can increase the efficiency of a randomized trial. While several model-based strategies for covariate adjustment have been developed—many of which can accommodate covariate-adjusted/adaptive randomization (CAR)—the potential benefits of CAR are less well understood, particularly regarding efficiency gains. Here, we examine the strengths and limitations of design-based covariate adjustment analyzed with randomization-based inference (i.e., CAR+RBI), review traditional and contemporary CAR methods, and provide a case study to assess the efficiency of CAR+RBI strategies. We ask the question: can adjusting for covariates only in the design be as powerful as adjusting for covariates only in the analysis?</p>
<p>The case study uses data from the REACH trial (n=512, 12-month continuous outcome with 9 baseline covariates explaining 32% of the outcome variance). We compare the power of CAR+RBI strategies to detect a beneficial treatment effect against that of complete randomization, analyzed with a comparable covariate-adjusted linear model. In this case study, biased-coin minimization CAR+RBI strategies were the most powerful strategies, suggesting that covariate adjustment in the design can be as effective as model-based covariate adjustment. While these findings are case-specific and results may differ across studies, they highlight the importance of further CAR and RBI research and consideration of implementation barriers.</p>
<p>This presentation summarizes the following paper, emphasizing the real-world application/case study.</p>
<p>Chipman JJ, Mayberry L, Greevy RA Jr (2023). Rematching on-the-fly: Sequential matched randomization and a case for covariate-adjusted randomization. Stat Med, 42(22), 3981-3995.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub6.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Automated, efficient and model-free inference for randomized clinical trials via data-driven covariate adjustment</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub5.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> Automated, efficient and model-free inference for randomized clinical trials via data-driven covariate adjustment</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: September 13th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Kelly Van Lancker from Ghent University</p>
<p><strong>Zoom link:</strong>: https://umich.zoom.us/j/7573650566</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> In May 2023, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) released guidance for industry on “Adjustment for Covariates in Randomized Clinical Trials for Drugs and Biological Products”. Covariate adjustment is a statistical analysis method for improving precision and power in clinical trials by adjusting for pre-specified, prognostic baseline variables. Though recommended by the FDA and the European Medicines Agency (EMA), many trials do not exploit the available information in baseline variables or make use only of the baseline measurement of the outcome. This is likely (partly) due to the regulatory mandate to pre-specify baseline covariates for adjustment, leading to challenges in determining appropriate covariates and their functional forms. We will explore the potential of automated data-adaptive methods, such as machine learning algorithms, for covariate adjustment, addressing the challenge of pre-specification. Specifically, our approach allows the use of complex models or machine learning algorithms without compromising the interpretation or validity of the treatment effect estimate and its corresponding standard error, even in the presence of misspecified outcome working models. This contrasts the majority of competing works which assume correct model specification for the validity of standard errors. Our proposed estimators either necessitate ultra-sparsity in the outcome model (which can be relaxed by limiting the number of predictors in the model) or necessitate integration with sample splitting to enhance their performance. As such, we will arrive at simple estimators and standard errors for the marginal treatment effect in randomized clinical trials, which exploit data-adaptive outcome predictions based on prognostic baseline covariates, and have low (or no) bias in finite samples even when those predictions are themselves biased.</p>
<p><strong>Recording:</strong></p>
<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/11eDNsw1fvUKyMsV7IfoN5Y14xsclij7C/preview" width="640" height="480" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="carswg/carswg.github.io" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLX8xOg" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLX8xOs4CeZQB" data-mapping="title" data-strict="1" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="light_high_contrast" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub5.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Strategies for Practical and Effective Covariate Adjustment of Continuous Outcomes</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> AStrategies for Practical and Effective Covariate Adjustment of Continuous Outcomes</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: June 14th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Michel Friesenhahn from Genentech</p>
<p><strong>Zoom link:</strong>: https://umich.zoom.us/j/7573650566</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> There has been considerable research that has put covariate adjustment on firm footing, even for use in the primary analysis of confirmatory clinical trials. Several of my colleagues and I saw there was a need to explain the insights generated from this research and to distill them into simple and practical suggestions for implementation. Our recommendations for continuous outcomes when primary interest is in unconditional treatment effect estimands, such as Average Treatment Effects (ATEs), are written up in blog form (https://stats4datascience.com/posts/covariate_adjustment/).</p>
<p>For this talk, I will discuss selected proposals from the blog that I think may be of particular interest to the working group, as well as potential areas for future work:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Performance metrics and their use in analyzing data external to a trial to select and/or construct covariates. In addition, I will discuss how these metrics provide insight into the impacts of Heterogeneous Treatment Effects (HTEs) and strategic implications for sample size determination.</p></li>
<li><p>The concept of a model budget and suggested rules of thumb to protect the validity of statistical inference when using covariate adjustment.</p></li>
<li><p>Suggestions for constructing the working regression model.</p></li>
<li><p>Accounting for stratified randomization.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally, I will discuss covariate adjustment of longitudinal data with continuous outcomes.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Recording:</strong></p>
<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/13_lHEYOOG_8PGRZ43GmP2O7OkMrDXDVq/preview" width="640" height="480" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<p><strong>Slides:</strong> https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ST83aTvH0A40KNusQ6-dg3IqdH3uaN5O/view?usp=drive_link</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="carswg/carswg.github.io" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLX8xOg" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLX8xOs4CeZQB" data-mapping="title" data-strict="1" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="light_high_contrast" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A General Form of Covariate Adjustment in Randomized Clinical Trials</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> A General Form of Covariate Adjustment in Randomized Clinical Trials</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: May 10th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Marlena Bannick from University of Washington</p>
<p><strong>Recording:</strong></p>
<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/167YZuPvqe1u-pKVNak82tzX1s_TdPJfG/preview" width="640" height="480" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<p><strong>Paper link:</strong> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10213" class="uri">https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10213</a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="carswg/carswg.github.io" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLX8xOg" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLX8xOs4CeZQB" data-mapping="title" data-strict="1" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="light_high_contrast" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Variance Estimation for G-computation with Binary Outcomes</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> Variance Estimation for G-computation with Binary Outcomes</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: April 12th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Presenter:</strong> Dominic Magirr from Novartis (20min presentation about comparisons of different methods)</p>
<p><strong>Discussants</strong>: Daniel Rubin, Dong Xi, and Ting Ye (20min discussion).</p>
<p><strong>Open-floor discussion:</strong> 20min.</p>
<p><strong>Recording:</strong></p>
<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ZVMlCLA996-nBRkmFbYa9sSn8w6KclDV/preview" width="640" height="480" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="carswg/carswg.github.io" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLX8xOg" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLX8xOs4CeZQB" data-mapping="title" data-strict="1" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="light_high_contrast" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Discussion on the FDA Guidance for Covariate Adjustment</title>
  <link>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Topic:</strong> Discussion on the FDA Guidance for Covariate Adjustment</p>
<p><strong>Datetime: March 15th Friday, 11am-12pm EDT</strong></p>
<p><strong>Host:</strong> Bingkai Wang (<em>UMich</em>)</p>
<p><strong>Discussants</strong>: Frank Bretz (<em>Novartis</em>), Daniel Rubin (<em>FDA</em>), and Ting Ye (<em>UWashington</em>)</p>
<p><strong>Open-floor discussion:</strong> 20min.</p>
<p><strong>Zoom link:</strong> <a href="https://upenn.zoom.us/j/4909817768" class="uri">https://upenn.zoom.us/j/4909817768</a></p>
<p><strong>Recording:</strong> <!-- [Journal-club-0315.mp4 - Google Drive](https://drive.google.com/file/d/1VSWw40RTpN2RLctit1gqs3Ld7o1FetEz/view?ts=65f481c3) --></p>
<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1VSWw40RTpN2RLctit1gqs3Ld7o1FetEz/preview" width="640" height="480" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay"></iframe>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="carswg/carswg.github.io" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLX8xOg" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLX8xOs4CeZQB" data-mapping="title" data-strict="1" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="light_high_contrast" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal club</category>
  <guid>https://carswg.github.io/journalclub/journalclub1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
